<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on CalcSheets</title>
    <link>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on CalcSheets</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Finding areas by slicing</title>
      <link>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/slice-area/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/slice-area/</guid>
      <description>Calculating the area of a region under a curve This cheat sheet covers using an integral to find the area of a region under a curve.
Introduction In previous chapters, we found the area under a curve by cutting it up into increasingly tiny rectangles (or other shapes) and adding their areas:
$\lim_{n \to \infty} \sum\limits_{i=0}^{n} (\frac{b-a}{n})*f(a+\frac{b-a}{n}k)$
This can be a good way to approximate the area under a curve, but it can be time consuming and is inexact.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;calculating-the-area-of-a-region-under-a-curve&#34;&gt;Calculating the area of a region under a curve&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cheat sheet covers using an integral to find the area of a region under a curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In previous chapters, we found the area under a curve by cutting it up into increasingly tiny rectangles (or other shapes) and adding their areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\lim_{n \to \infty} \sum\limits_{i=0}^{n} (\frac{b-a}{n})*f(a+\frac{b-a}{n}k)$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be a good way to approximate the area under a curve, but it can be time consuming and is inexact. This chapter focuses on using an integral to find the area under a curve instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\int_a^b f(x) dx$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we know how to find the area under the curve, however, we can use the same techniques to find the area of any region bounded by one or more curves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-to-know&#34;&gt;Things to Know&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before diving into using the integral to find the area under a curve, there are a few important things to keep in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The integral is a sum of infinitely many rectangles, so it is exact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The integral is the opposite of the derivative, so the integral of a derivative is the original function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculating-the-area-under-a-curve&#34;&gt;Calculating the Area under a curve&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To calculate the area under a curve, we need to find the integral of the function that describes the curve. For example, if we want to find the area under the curve $y = x^2$, we need to find the integral of $x^2$:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\int x^2 dx = \frac{1}{3}x^3 + C$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $C$ is a constant of integration. To find the area under the curve, we need to evaluate the integral at the upper and lower bounds of the curve:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\int_a^b f(x) dx = F(a) - F(b) = \lim_{n \to b-}F(a) - \lim_{n \to b-}F(b)$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $F(x)$ is the integral of $f(x)$. Recalling that $F(x)=\frac{1}{3}x^3 + C$, we can apply the definition to find the area:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\int_0^1 x^2 dx = \frac{1}{3} - 0 = \frac{1}{3}$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculating-the-area-of-a-triangular-region&#34;&gt;Calculating the Area of a triangular region&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finding the area under a curve is all well and good, but the real power comes from using the same techniques to find the area of &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; region bounded by curves. For example, if we want to find the area of an isosceles triangle with base $10$ and height $5$, we could use the triangle area formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\text{Area} = \frac{1}{2}\text{base} * \text{height}$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we don&amp;rsquo;t know the formula, or a general formula simply does not exist? &lt;em&gt;We can use an integral!&lt;/em&gt; To use an integral to find the area of the triangle, we will need to use a reimann sum to find the area of the triangle. We can do this by cutting the triangle up into infinitely many rectangles, and then adding their areas. To do this, we will need a few more bits of data. We know the formula of the rectangle area that we will be using ($\text{Area} = \text{base} * \text{height}$). We will know the height ($\Delta x$) of each rectangle, but we need to be able to find the base in terms of height, where given a height from the bottom of the triangle, we can find the corresponding width.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$[\frac{w_i}{10} = \frac{5-h_i}{5}] = [w_i=2(5-h_i)] = \textcolor{#ff6600}{[w_i=10-2h_i]}$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we have a function that gives us the width of the subrectangles, we can construct a summation representing the area of the triangle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\sum\limits_{i=0}^{n}w_i\Delta h=\sum\limits_{i=0}^{n}\textcolor{#ff6600}{10-2h_i}\Delta h\text{ cm}^2$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By taking the limit to infinity, we can get the integral for the area of the triangle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\sum\limits_{i=0}^{n}{10-2h_i}\Delta h\ = \int_0^5(10-2h)dh\text{ cm}^2$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, by evaluating the integral at the upper and lower bounds, we can find the area of the triangle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$(10h-2h)\Bigg|_0^5=25\text{ cm}^2$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And as a final step, checking our work with the traditional formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\frac{1}{2}10*5=25\text{ cm}^2$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;calculating-the-area-of-a-semi-circular-region&#34;&gt;Calculating the Area of a semi-circular region&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can use the same techniques to find the area of any region bounded by curves. For example, if we want to find the area of a semi-circle with radius $7$, we can use the circle area formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\text{Area} = \pi r^2$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just like triangles, we can use the integral to find this instead!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like the triangle, the first step is to find the area of a single rectangle, and to do so, we need to calculate the width of a rectangle at a given height. While it is slightly more complex than on the triangle, it is still pretty easy to determine this function using the pythagorean theorem, where $h$ is $a$, and $w$ is $b$:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$[h_i^2+(\frac{w_i}{2})=7^2] = [w_i=\sqrt{4(7^2-h^2_i)}] = \textcolor{#ff6600}{[w_i=2\sqrt{49-h_i^2}]}$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And a summation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\sum\limits_{i=0}^{n}w_i\Delta h=\sum\limits_{i=0}^{n}\textcolor{#ff6600}{2\sqrt{49-h_i^2}}\Delta h\text{ cm}^2$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And taking the limit to infinity to get the integral:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\sum\limits_{i=0}^{n}{2\sqrt{49-h_i^2}}\Delta h\ = 2\int_0^7(\sqrt{49-h^2})dh\text{ cm}^2$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, evaluating the integral using the table of integrals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$2*\frac{1}{2}(h\sqrt{49-h^2}+49arcsin(\frac{h}{7}))\Bigg|_0^7=49arcsin(1)=\frac{49}{2}\pi$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And checking our work with the traditional formula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\frac12\pi7^2=\frac{49}{2}\pi$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the integral to find the area of any curve is an extremely powerful skill to have because once we are able to determine the area of any 2d shape, we are able to determine the volume of any 3d shape.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrations with Physics</title>
      <link>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/physics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/physics/</guid>
      <description>Basic Calculus Integrations with Physics This cheat sheet covers basic calculus integrations commonly used in physics applications, including position, velocity, acceleration, force, work, and energy.
Introduction Calculus plays a crucial role in physics, as it allows us to analyze and understand the behavior of physical systems by describing how they change over time. In particular, calculus integrations are used to calculate important physical quantities, such as position, velocity, acceleration, force, work, and energy.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;basic-calculus-integrations-with-physics&#34;&gt;Basic Calculus Integrations with Physics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cheat sheet covers basic calculus integrations commonly used in physics applications, including position, velocity, acceleration, force, work, and energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculus plays a crucial role in physics, as it allows us to analyze and understand the behavior of physical systems by describing how they change over time. In particular, calculus integrations are used to calculate important physical quantities, such as position, velocity, acceleration, force, work, and energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-to-know&#34;&gt;Things to Know&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into the specific calculus integrations used in physics, there are a few important things to keep in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In physics, calculus is typically used to analyze motion and forces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most common calculus integrations used in physics are those related to position, velocity, acceleration, force, work, and energy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Calculus integrations can be used to analyze both linear and rotational motion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;position&#34;&gt;Position&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Position is a key concept in physics that describes an object&amp;rsquo;s location in space. Calculus integrations can be used to determine an object&amp;rsquo;s position at any given time, given its initial position and velocity. The calculus integration for position is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Position: $x(t) = \int v(t) dt + x_0$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $x(t)$ is the position of the object at time $t$, $v(t)$ is its velocity at time $t$, $x_0$ is its initial position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;velocity&#34;&gt;Velocity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Velocity describes an object&amp;rsquo;s speed and direction of motion. Calculus integrations can be used to determine an object&amp;rsquo;s velocity at any given time, given its initial velocity and acceleration. The calculus integration for velocity is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Velocity: $v(t) = \int a(t) dt + v_0$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $v(t)$ is the velocity of the object at time $t$, $a(t)$ is its acceleration at time $t$, and $v_0$ is its initial velocity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;acceleration&#34;&gt;Acceleration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acceleration describes the rate of change of an object&amp;rsquo;s velocity. Calculus integrations can be used to determine an object&amp;rsquo;s acceleration at any given time, given its initial acceleration and the net force acting on it. The calculus integration for acceleration is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Acceleration: $a(t) = \frac{1}{m} \int F(t) dt + a_0$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $a(t)$ is the acceleration of the object at time $t$, $m$ is its mass, $F(t)$ is the net force acting on it at time $t$, and $a_0$ is its initial acceleration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;force&#34;&gt;Force&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Force describes the influence that one object has on another, causing it to accelerate. Calculus integrations can be used to determine the work done by a force, as well as the potential energy associated with a force. The calculus integration for force is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work: $W = \int F(x) dx$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potential Energy: $U(x) = -\int F(x) dx$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $W$ is the work done by the force, $F(x)$ is the force acting on an object at position $x$, and $U(x)$ is the potential energy associated with the force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;energy&#34;&gt;Energy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Energy is a fundamental concept in physics that describes an object&amp;rsquo;s ability to do work. Calculus integrations can be used to determine an object&amp;rsquo;s kinetic energy, as well as its potential energy. The calculus integration for energy is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Kinetic Energy: $K = \frac{1}{2} mv^2$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Potential Energy: $U(x) = -\int F(x) dx$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $K$ is the kinetic energy of the object, $m$ is its mass, $v$ is its velocity, $F(x)$ is the force acting on an object at position $x$, and $U(x)$ is the potential energy associated with the force.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Calculus integrations are essential tools for understanding and analyzing physical systems. By using these integrations, we can determine important physical quantities such as position, velocity, acceleration, force, work, and energy. By mastering these basic calculus integrations, you will be better equipped to solve a wide range of physics problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Limits</title>
      <link>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/limit/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/limit/</guid>
      <description>Limits Limits are a fundamental concept in calculus that allow us to understand the behavior of functions as they approach certain values or infinity.
Introduction Limits are a way to analyze the behavior of functions as they approach certain values. They are used to define derivatives and integrals, and are a crucial tool for solving a wide range of mathematical problems.
Things to Know Before we dive into the rules for solving limits, there are a few important things to keep in mind:</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;limits&#34;&gt;Limits&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limits are a fundamental concept in calculus that allow us to understand the behavior of functions as they approach certain values or infinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Limits are a way to analyze the behavior of functions as they approach certain values. They are used to define derivatives and integrals, and are a crucial tool for solving a wide range of mathematical problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-to-know&#34;&gt;Things to Know&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into the rules for solving limits, there are a few important things to keep in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limits are typically denoted using the symbol $\lim_{x \to a}$, which means &amp;ldquo;the limit of f(x) as x approaches a&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The limit of a function f(x) at a point a is the value that f(x) approaches as x gets arbitrarily close to a.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rules for solving limits depend on the form of the function being evaluated and the technique used to evaluate it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Limits can be evaluated using direct substitution, factoring, rationalization, conjugation, or other techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-problem&#34;&gt;Example Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with a simple practice problem to illustrate how limits work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the limit of $f(x) = 2x + 1$ as $x$ approaches $3$ (denoted as $\lim_{x \to 3} (2x + 1)$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find the limit, we simply substitute $3$ for $x$ in the expression $2x + 1$:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$\lim_{x \to 3} (2x + 1) = 2(3) + 1 = 7$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the limit of $f(x) = 2x + 1$ as $x$ approaches $3$ is $7$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;common-rules&#34;&gt;Common Rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several common rules for solving limits, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Direct Substitution: If the function is defined at the point being evaluated, then simply plug in the value and evaluate the limit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Factoring: If the function is in a fraction form, factor out the common factor and simplify the expression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rationalization: If the function has a square root or cube root in the numerator or denominator, multiply by the conjugate to simplify the expression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;L&amp;rsquo;Hopital&amp;rsquo;s Rule: If the function has the form $\frac{0}{0}$ or $\frac{\infty}{\infty}$, then use L&amp;rsquo;Hopital&amp;rsquo;s Rule to evaluate the limit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Squeeze Theorem: If the function is between two other functions that have the same limit, then the function being evaluated has the same limit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that these rules are just a starting point and not all limits can be solved using just these techniques. It&amp;rsquo;s important to practice and get familiar with these techniques to develop your intuition for solving limits.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Derivative</title>
      <link>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/derivative/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/derivative/</guid>
      <description>The Derivative The derivative is a fundamental concept in calculus that allows us to analyze the rate of change of a function and find the slope of a curve at any point.
Introduction The derivative is a mathematical tool that allows us to analyze the rate of change of a function and find the slope of a curve at any point. It is a fundamental concept in calculus and is used in many areas of science, engineering, and economics.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-derivative&#34;&gt;The Derivative&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The derivative is a fundamental concept in calculus that allows us to analyze the rate of change of a function and find the slope of a curve at any point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The derivative is a mathematical tool that allows us to analyze the rate of change of a function and find the slope of a curve at any point. It is a fundamental concept in calculus and is used in many areas of science, engineering, and economics. Understanding derivatives is crucial for solving a wide range of mathematical problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-to-know&#34;&gt;Things to Know&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into the rules for finding derivatives, there are a few important things to keep in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The derivative is denoted using the symbol $f&amp;rsquo;(x)$, which means &amp;ldquo;the derivative of f(x) with respect to x&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The derivative of a function f(x) at a point x is the slope of the tangent line to the curve of f(x) at that point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rules for finding derivatives depend on the form of the function being differentiated and the technique used to differentiate it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Derivatives can be used to analyze the behavior of functions, find maximum and minimum values, and solve optimization problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-problem&#34;&gt;Example Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with a simple practice problem to illustrate how to find derivatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the derivative of $f(x) = 3x^2 - 4x + 1$:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the derivative of $f(x) = 3x^2 - 4x + 1$ is $f&amp;rsquo;(x) = 6x - 4$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find the derivative, we use the power rule, which states that the derivative of a function of the form $f(x) = x^n$ is $f&amp;rsquo;(x) = nx^{n-1}$. We apply this rule to each term in the expression $f(x) = 3x^2 - 4x + 1$:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The derivative of the first term $3x^2$ is $6x$, since $2 \cdot 3x^{2-1} = 6x$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The derivative of the second term $-4x$ is $-4$, since $1 \cdot -4x^{1-1} = -4$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The derivative of the third term $1$ is $0$, since the derivative of a constant is always $0$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Putting these results together, we get:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$f&amp;rsquo;(x) = 6x - 4 + 0 = 6x - 4$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the derivative of $f(x) = 3x^2 - 4x + 1$ is $f&amp;rsquo;(x) = 6x - 4$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that the derivative of a function represents the instantaneous rate of change of the function at any given point. In this case, the derivative $f&amp;rsquo;(x) = 6x - 4$ tells us that the rate of change of the function $f(x) = 3x^2 - 4x + 1$ increases at a rate of $6$ units per unit of $x$. We can also use the derivative to find the slope of the tangent line to the curve of $f(x)$ at any point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;common-rules&#34;&gt;Common Rules&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several common rules for finding derivatives, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Rule: $\frac{d}{dx} x^n = nx^{n-1}$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constant Multiple Rule: $\frac{d}{dx} cf(x) = c\frac{d}{dx} f(x)$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sum and Difference Rule: $\frac{d}{dx} [f(x) \pm g(x)] = \frac{d}{dx} f(x) \pm \frac{d}{dx} g(x)$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Product Rule: $\frac{d}{dx} [f(x)g(x)] = f(x)\frac{d}{dx} g(x) + g(x)\frac{d}{dx} f(x)$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quotient Rule: $\frac{d}{dx} \frac{f(x)}{g(x)} = \frac{g(x)\frac{d}{dx} f(x) - f(x)\frac{d}{dx} g(x)}{g(x)^2}$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Chain Rule: $\frac{d}{dx} f(g(x)) = f&amp;rsquo;(g(x))g&amp;rsquo;(x)$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Implicit Differentiation: If a function is defined implicitly, we can still find its derivative by differentiating both sides of the equation with respect to x.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that these rules are just a starting point and not all derivatives can be found using just these techniques. It&amp;rsquo;s important to practice and get familiar with these techniques to develop your intuition for finding derivatives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The derivative is a powerful mathematical tool that allows us to analyze the rate of change of a function and find the slope of a curve at any point. It is a fundamental concept in calculus and is used in many areas of science, engineering, and economics. By understanding the rules for finding derivatives and practicing&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Integral</title>
      <link>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/integral/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://math.jackcrane.rocks/pages/integral/</guid>
      <description>The Integral Integrals are a powerful mathematical tool for calculating the area under a curve and determining the volumes and surface areas of complex shapes.
Introduction Integrals are a fundamental concept in calculus that allow us to calculate the total sum of infinitely small pieces of a curve or shape. They are used in many areas of science, engineering, and economics, and are an essential tool for solving a wide range of mathematical problems.</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-integral&#34;&gt;The Integral&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrals are a powerful mathematical tool for calculating the area under a curve and determining the volumes and surface areas of complex shapes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Integrals are a fundamental concept in calculus that allow us to calculate the total sum of infinitely small pieces of a curve or shape. They are used in many areas of science, engineering, and economics, and are an essential tool for solving a wide range of mathematical problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;things-to-know&#34;&gt;Things to Know&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we dive into the rules for solving integrals, there are a few important things to keep in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The integral sign is denoted by the symbol $\int$ and is used to indicate integration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The variable of integration is typically denoted by $dx$ or $dy$, and represents the infinitely small width or height of the curve being integrated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integrals can be solved either analytically or numerically, depending on the complexity of the function being integrated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rules for solving integrals depend on the form of the function being integrated and the technique used to solve it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;example-problem&#34;&gt;Example Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with a simple practice problem to illustrate how integrals work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find the integral of $f(x) = x^2$ from $x=0$ to $x=1$:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is $\int_0^1 x^2 dx = \frac{1}{3}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Common Rules
There are several common rules for solving integrals, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power Rule: $\int x^n dx = \frac{x^{n+1}}{n+1} + C$ for all $n \neq -1$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exponential Rule: $\int e^x dx = e^x + C$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trigonometric Rules: $\int \sin(x) dx = -\cos(x) + C, \quad \int \cos(x) dx = \sin(x) + C$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration by Substitution: $\int f(g(x))g&amp;rsquo;(x) dx = \int f(u) du$, where $u = g(x)$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integration by Parts: $\int u dv = uv - \int v du$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trigonometric Substitution: $\int \sqrt{a^2 - x^2} dx = \frac{1}{a^2} \arcsin(\frac{x}{a}) + C$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Partial Fraction Decomposition: $\int \frac{Ax + B}{x^2 + px + q} dx = \frac{A}{2} \ln(x^2 + px + q) + (B - \frac{Ap}{2}) \int \frac{dx}{x^2 + px + q}$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improper Integrals: $\int f(x) dx$ from $a$ to $b$, where either $a$ or $b$ is $\pm \infty$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Definite Integrals: $\int_a^b f(x) dx$ gives the signed area between the curve $f(x)$ and the x-axis, from $x=a$ to $x=b$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that these rules are just a starting point and not all integrals can be solved using just these techniques. It&amp;rsquo;s important to practice and get familiar with these techniques to develop your intuition for solving integrals.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
